RG 004:129, Somers Probate Court
Connecticut State Library
Somers Probate Court records
1834-1947
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Probate Court (Somers District)
11.25 cubic feet
Record books, 1834-1947; Probate files, 1834-1941.
RG004_129
1911-010 and 2011-003
Historical Note
Somers, Tolland County, Town established in July 1734, Parent Town: Part of Massachusetts until May, 1749
The Somers Probate District was constituted June 3, 1834 from the Ellington Probate District. The Somers Probate District merged with the Stafford Probate District on January 6, 1999. The Stafford Probate merged with the Enfield Probate District on January 5, 2011 to create the North Central Probate District which serves the municipalities of Enfield, Somers, Stafford, and Union.
Town of Somers, Probate District chronology:
July 1734 - May 1749, Hampshire County Massachusetts Jurisdiction
May 1749 - May 1759, Hartford District
May 1759 - May 1826, Stafford District
May 1826 - June 2, 1834, Ellington District
June 3, 1834 - January 5, 1999, Somers District
January 6, 1999 - January 4, 2011, Stafford District
January 5, 2011 - Present, North Central Connecticut District
For Probate Court contact information and hours of operation see,.
Scope and Content
Probate record books, volumes 1-16, 1834-1947. Contact the probate court to access original record books numbered after 16. See Alternative Form Available note below.
Probate files, 1834-1941. Probate files may consist of estates, conservatorships, guardianships, commitments, and insolvencies. See Alternative Form Available note below.
Inventory control book, 1834-1941 (coverage). Also known as the Godard Digest, it is a list of probate files transferred to the Connecticut State Library. It was compiled at the Connecticut State Library under the direction of State Librarian George S. Godard.
Arrangement
Record books in accession 2011-003 are numnbered 1 to 16.
Probate files in accession 1911-010 are arranged alphabetically.
Other Finding Aid
Record Books: Index cards for the record books have been scanned. Ask History and Genealogy staff for assistance. See Alternate Form Available section for volumes available on microfilm.
Probate Files: The Probate Estate Papers Index, located in the index corridor adjacent to the History and Genealogy Reading Room, has two parts, a general index covering most of the state, and a Hartford Probate District index covering Hartford and some surrounding towns, 1820-1920. The index cards are arranged alphabetically by individual's last name and first names. The cards have the individual's name, town of residence, probate district, and list of items contained in the estate packet. To request retrieval of an estate packet, copy at least the estate name, file date, and probate district name from the index card. The probate files in Accession 1911-010 are represented in this index.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Probate records -- Connecticut -- Somers
Places:
Somers (Conn.)
Restrictions on Access
Researchers should first consult use copies when available. See Alternate Form Available Section below.
Accession 2011-003, Record books, 1834-1947, is stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
Probate files dated 1921 or later are RESTRICTED pending review by State Archives staff as they may contain confidential documents. Tax returns (succession, transfer and estate tax returns and all attachments) from January 1, 1921 and later are confidential per Connecticut General Statutes §12-15. Adoptions (all documents) from January 1, 1944 and later are confidential per Connecticut General Statutes §45a-754. Removals of parent as guardian of minor (all documents) and terminations of parental rights (all documents) from October 1, 1975 and later are confidential per Connecticut General Statutes §45a-754. Contact State Archives staff for assistance. Adoptions (all documents) from January 1, 1944 and later are confidential per Connecticut General Statutes §45a-754. Contact State Archives staff for assistance.
See the policy.
Alternative Form Available
Record books, volumes 1-11, 1834-1919; probate files, 1834-1880 (Accession 1911-010); and inventory control book (Godard Digest) were microfilmed by the Genealogical Society of Utah and are available for use in the History and Genealogy reading room or through the.
Provenance
The probate files in accession 1911-010 were transferred to the Connecticut State Library on the following dates (with date span of files): November 14, 1911 (1834-1909); October 27, 1920 (1887-1918); October 26, 1923 (1889-1921); December 19, 1928 (1891-1928); August 15, 1933(1901-1932); January 26, 1937 (1908-1936); November 18, 1942 (1869-1941). They were interfiled into one alphabetic sequence.
The record books in accession 2011-003 were transferred to the Connecticut State Library on July 7, 2010.
Container List
- Record books, 1834-1947; 7.5 cubic feet (16 volumes); 2011-003
  - Records, 1834-1853 (Volume 1)
    On spine: "Ledger"
  - Decrees, 1835-1851 (Volume 2)
  - Records, 1851-1861 (Volume 3)
  - Records, 1861-1869 (Volume 4)
  - Records, 1869-1881 (Volume 5)
  - Records, 1881-1889 (Volume 6)
  - Decrees, 1889-1905 (Volume 7)
  - Records, 1894-1904 (Volume 8)
    On spine: "Miscellaneous"
  - Records, 1904-1912 (Volume 9)
  - Decrees, 1908-1938 (Volume 10)
  - Records, 1912-1919 (Volume 11)
  - Records, 1917-1927 (Volume 12)
  - Records, 1927-1933 (Volume 13)
  - Records, 1833-1841 (Volume 14)
  - Decrees, 1939-1945 (Volume 15)
  - Records, 1941-1947 (Volume 16)
- Probate files, 1834-1941; 4.25 cubic feet; 1911-010
  - Aborn - Billings, M. (Drawer 1)
  - Billings, N. - Fradett (Drawer 2)
  - Frost - Kibbe, M. (Drawer 3)
  - Kibbe, N. - Phipps (Drawer 4)
  - Pinney - Z.; Miscellaneous (Drawer 5)
- Inventory Control Book, 1834-1941; T003073
  Index of the seven accessions of probate files now merged into accession 1911-010
  Also known as the Godard Digest